Ah, cannot do this one a Render fighter.
APPLAUSE
Would you do me a favour?
I'd like to stop talking for a minute, and when I do,
take a look at the room you're in, and above all,
at the man-made objects in that room that surround you,
the television set, the lights, the phone and so on.
And ask yourself, what those objects do to your life,
just because they're there? Go ahead.
Well, that is what this series is going to be all about.
It's about the things that surround you in the modern world,
and just because they're there, shape the way you think and behave.
And why they exist in the form they do, and who or what was responsible for them existing at all.
The search for those clues will take us all over the world,
and 12,000 years into the past, because it's in those strange places,
and in those long gone centuries, that the secret of the modern world lies.
And you never believe the extraordinary things that led to us being the way we are today.
Things like, for instance, why a 16th century doctor at the Court of Queen Elizabeth
did something that made it possible for you to watch this screen now?
Or the fact that because 18th century merchants were worried about ships' bottoms,
you have nylon to wear.
Or why a group of French monks and their involvement with sheep rearing
up to give the modern world the computer.
Or what medieval Europeans did with their fire in winter that led to motor car manufacture.
The story of the events and the people who, over centuries,
came together to bring us in from the cold,
and to wrap us in a warm blanket of technology is a matter of vital importance,
since more and more of that technology infiltrates every aspect of our lives.
It's become a life support system, without which we can't survive.
And yet, how much of it do we understand?
Do I bother myself with the reality of what happens when I get into a big steel box,
press a button and rise into the sky?
Of course I don't.
S Henderson.
Well I don't think it'd keep me here last but it'd have to kill the beast because of the
I take going up in the world like that for granted. We all do. And as the years of the
20th century have gone by, the things we take for granted have multiplied way beyond the
ability of any individual to understand in a lifetime. The things around us, the man-made
inventions we provide ourselves with are like a vast network, each part of which is
interdependent with all the others. I mean, cross the road. Whether or not a car coming
around the corner knocks you down. May have something to do with the person you've never
met fitting the brakes correctly. Change anything in that network and the effects spread like
ripples on a pond. And all the things in that network have become so specialised that only
the people involved in making them understand them. I don't mean use them, anybody can use
them. Down there is one of the biggest, most complex cities in the world, full of people
using things as if they understood them. And sometimes not even knowing they're doing
it. New York City, like all the other major high-density
population centres scattered across the earth, is a technology island. It can either feed
nor close nor house nor warm its inhabitants without supplies from outside. Without those
supplies, the entire massive structure and the teeming millions it encloses would die.
And yet, in cities everywhere, we act as if that were not so. We have no choice. The pace
of life in New York is set by the pace of the technology that serves it. You just have
to hope it will stay that way.
I'd like you to meet a few people who were in or near New York City on a November evening
over a decade ago. And the reason I'd like you to meet them is because they all have
one thing in common. They were all brought to a sudden and catastrophic realisation
of how vulnerable they were, how dependent on one aspect of that technological network
I was talking about, because of what this did to their lives. Now, until I was told what
this is, I was no more able to recognise what it is than you are now. But what's what it
did to those people. And if you look very carefully, you'll see evidence of what this
does in every second of what follows now.
It's one minute past five in the evening, rush hour in downtown Manhattan. 800,000 people
crowd onto subways looking forward to hope to the end of this journey. For most of them,
the technology carrying them doesn't exist. They take it for granted.
Two minutes past five. Kennedy Airport, the usual evening departure rate, passengers with
appointments in New Delhi, London, Tokyo. Appointments they expect to keep. And 200
planes due to arrive in the next five hours.
No delays expected. Three minutes past five. At the energy control centre downtown, nothing
special is happening. It's the standard rush hour condition in the main control room. The
time of day when power consumption started to come up to a maximum as people head for
home and meals get cooked. It's cool outside after a high of 58, the temperature is falling
to an expected low of 39 with a predicted wind chill factor of five degrees. The energy
levels are more than enough to cook, even on a chilly November evening.
Ten past five. Mount Sinai Hospital.
I'm just giving you an option to know how good the cycle is in your way.
The patient, Mrs. Marcanna, is expecting twins.
Thank you, Mr. Chairman. May I first say to my distinguished colleague, the ambassador
from the U.S. S.O.
Twelve minutes past five, the UN General Assembly in session. The speaker is President Roosevelt's
son. In their boxes, the interpreters, the invisible support structure of the debate,
whatever the language, at the UN, that's taken for granted.
The way that means worship remains equally.
In the subway, Herbert Friedman, a lawyer, reads his paper on his way home to suburban
Jamaica. Al Hennick works for a publisher on Fifth Avenue. He passes the time doing a
crossword. Marjorie O'Shaughnessy also works for a publisher, looking forward to spending
a quiet evening at home.
Steve Boatti, late, been to a movie. Bruce Singer works in Greenwich Village. Bill Palmer
is a student, just been playing basketball. And Hans Kramer, insurance broker. All these
people take the subway every evening. They expect to get home. They always do.
The flight manifest lists 89 passengers. The descent into Kennedy is so far uneventful.
It's now 15 minutes and 30 seconds past five.
With the next contraction, you'll take a deep breath and push real hard. Okay. I think
you can put it asleep now. The anesthetic being used at the time as a mixture of gases,
including one called cyclopropane. It's potentially explosive. But everybody knows that.
Okay. It's fairly sleepy now. Okay. With the next contraction, we'll have a little bit
of pressure. All right. When she's starting contraction now. It's a little bit more.
Okay. Okay. Okay. We've got a baby. It's now exactly 16 minutes and 10 seconds past
five. One second later, several hundred miles northwest of New York City. This did what it
was built to do with disastrous consequences. You may have already guessed what kind of
technological network this is part of. It's a bit of a power station. The power station
known as Adam Beck to here at Niagara, where electricity is generated by the tremendous
power of falling water. The water turns turbine blades that make a shaft spin at the top of
the shaft are magnets and they spin inside a cylinder up there that has copper wire coils
on its inner wall. The interaction between the spinning magnets and the copper coils makes
electricity. That's where this comes in. It's a relay and its job is to detect changes in
power going on to a transmission line. These up here. Power flows north along these lines.
And on a particular evening in question, this relay detected an increase in power on one
of those lines that was above a preset limit. When that happened, magnets set around this
metal cup caused it to rotate and that brought this arm to make a contact like this. That
contact was made on the evening of November the 9th, 1965 at 16 minutes and 11 seconds
past five. The effect was to cascade power off the overloaded line and onto another, which
overloaded and tripped the next until all five lines going north had tripped out dumping their
entire load onto lines going south. Within seven seconds, the tremendous overload began
to take out generating stations all over North Eastern America from Boston to New York as the
network fell apart. As each area went, it overloaded the next. Within ten seconds, the only major
system left was the great energy island of New York. As the network fell apart, links
between one energy centre and another broke. Instead of 300,000 kilowatts coming into New
York to help meet demand, one and a half million kilowatts were draining out of the city to supply
areas now cut off from the network but still connected like leeches to the New York generators.
As the overload hit the New York generators, they too began to trip out.
Hello, little five lines. And your ducking speed is okay, your brakes are all in.
We're in it out. We're in it out. We've been over two right now.
We've had a major power here. We're in it out.
We're likely to main orbit on all the speed of light with the jurner humps and marine auxiliary generator.
As the lifeblood of the city drained, it went into spasm.
At the UN, chaos, the power to keep the lights on also served the interpreters.
Who in the growing darkness has, however, I hope, brought a glimmer of light.
And without interpreters trapped in their darkened boxes, deprived of access to the ears of the
delegate. The United Nations was suddenly and totally disunited, as completely as if at war.
The city's elevators stopped.
Perhaps the subways were the only technology that people expected to fail.
800,000 people were now deep in the ground under New York.
Caught in a technology trap, most of them had never thought twice about.
As light went, so did the one in Mrs. Marcanna's operating theater.
It was now only 10 minutes since the crisis had been triggered by the relay at Niagara,
more than 500 miles away.
The generators continued to trip out, and at Kennedy Airport, the radar screens went black.
And slight 911 was in trouble.
And all I got, flag warning, switched number two to the island.
Okay?
Kennedy, up, up.
Yeah, who we got? Yeah, John?
Can you hold it at two, 50?
I'll take 200 if I can.
What time do you go out?
A story at 2-1-3 went out. They can't hold on.
By 5-28, the time had come to protect the system by deliberately switching what was left off.
We shut down those lights and Brooklyn's challenging left going.
Our killer's in front of the...
There are gummies.
They're not worried about it all alone, but they're out to kill the unit.
We leave that in or shut it down?
Oh, we've got to shut it down, I guess.
The system operator recommends shutting down Staten Island.
Yeah, and I'm not worried what you'll find out, all right?
From all that stuff.
Thank you.
Over an area of 80 million square miles, 30 million people were now in darkness.
The boat was down.
That's right.
Oh boy, how was this?
John, have a good chamois on the phone.
I saluted from each other in small groups.
Millions of people were still unaware of the extent of the blackout.
In the subway, especially.
It's not like the readings.
People started chatting, but for the most part, no one really got into it yet,
because we thought it was just another typical rush hour delay.
But it was dark, and that was kind of on 7 to be in such a crowd,
but not to be able to see anybody.
So one of the women had candles in her bag.
You know, I have some candles, and you can like them.
This abnormal business of actually talking to anybody on the subway,
caught on briefly all over New York.
Let's put some light on the situation.
My birthday anyway, anybody feel like singing?
No, you're a happy person.
Make a happy situation, and a terrible one.
My name?
Louise?
Happy birthday to you.
Happy birthday.
But while this journey had taken on a meaning,
nobody expected.
So too, at the hospital, had Mrs. Marcan as delivery of twins,
thanks to the anesthetic.
It was in a general story around to find flashlights,
and I immediately come on the other one,
so I see what would happen.
One of the nurses of course, I'll never forget,
grew up in the room carrying a light of candle.
Put the candle out.
Get out of here.
What's going on?
Just get out of my mind with the explosive anesthetic agent.
I had visions of all of us.
The whole place blowing up one great conflagration.
No.
The phone system was the only thing working
if you could get a number.
No.
It's a sipperto, Brian.
I can't see the runway.
And Captain Loster was learning the full extent of his predicament.
ILS, the landing aid that guided him in, wasn't there anymore.
It needs check the radio.
The military approach controls Canadian 911.
The ILS went US.
I've got some on.
Already the guys are caked.
The extraordinary thing in the subways was that a full hour into the crisis nobody was
trying to escape from the trap.
Yeah, it's not even a quick strip.
Would it be crooked to put one in man?
Yeah.
Okay.
Now what we need is a knife.
How are we going to?
I think I have something for it.
Now you know.
We need now the cups.
We need a good cup.
Got a wish.
The wishes that we get home tonight.
We need to get a little bit of the size of it.
Yes, good health to the person.
I'm going to get a little bit of the cup.
I'm going to get a little bit of the glass.
I just assumed that something went wrong with a particular train that I was riding on.
There was a feeling of it's being something we all just had to wait out together.
There was nothing anybody could do about it.
No one knew anything about anything.
Waynecks.
I carry napkins around.
I wipe those seats off so I don't get my clothes dirty.
Put your silk in this position.
Oh.
Do you know any different?
Here they were.
They were going to get into a major disaster and still trying to laugh their way out of it.
Drink and wine in the subway outside
of that.
Help yourself.
If anybody's driving don't drink.
Remember that.
How about singing the song?
How about moving the songs?
I have a wet fire and a watercoat and bed.
Whoa.
People began to be very jovial and began to sing.
Show me the way to go home and everything that people could think of that related to
our plight.
Let's just keep on going on.
At the hospital darkness made no difference.
I got the speech.
My bridge arrived.
Here we go.
All the head down.
I'm fine.
All right.
Well the baby was delivered without the lights because you didn't need the lights for the
delivery.
That's manipulative.
Remember you're reaching up into the uterus, grabbing a foot which is strictly by feel.
You're up to the membranes and you bring the foot down.
The second baby was vigorous and we repaired the piece.
There you go.
You're such a pretty girl.
Yes.
Kennedy approach the drive.
We're going to have your 9-11.
Captain Lostid had only a few seconds left to make his decision.
He was at 2,000 feet past the airport and heading straight for Manhattan in the darkness.
There was only one thing he could do.
Lostid and 200 other jets that night landed with the help of radio working on planes sitting
on the ground.
In the subway people were still coping.
But after an hour and a half people became very restless.
It was not pleasant.
It was not very congenial but everybody felt scared.
There had been this late plan you sit here and wonder and wonder and send nobody down
to help us.
Somebody knocked on the window and see if he would have turned to the test.
After about an hour and a half of these train employees would pass outside but not look
at us and not answer us when people banked on the windows and called out.
They just ignored us.
I think he's a conductor from the train but I'm not sure.
The scrunchie and the turning road.
The baby is going for help.
Oh, let's hold the pin.
Finally, people began to realise where they were.
Lost under the ground.
Helpless.
Unless helped came.
When we have a major power blackout at least hits the entire city.
It's all relaxed.
We'll be trying to get you over as soon as possible.
I'm leaving.
It's taking you a higher action.
You would have to be in between stations.
You happen to be on a platform?
I don't know how long this will take.
It's kind of innocent and it affects the entire city.
We have people coming by and evacuating the trains now.
Please relax.
Mrs. McConner found out what had happened to her.
So not the way she expected.
Mrs. McConner, what was that?
Work, work, work.
When I woke up and I saw all the candles lit around the room,
I thought I was dead and there was a priest standing nearby.
And for a minute there, I thought he had come to give me my last rights
and I was afraid that all my family knew that I was dead
and they came to light candles for me.
No, no, no, you're not playing more than I was playing more than that.
You're most of them were at the door.
Don't be frightened now.
You're going to be okay.
And finally, as in all good ferry stories, it was over.
In exactly five hours after the train stopped at 10.30,
the train began to empty by having all the passengers walk out
singly upon the catwalk.
A few days later, people were back at their daily routine
as if it had never happened.
The night New York became a trap, forgot.
I was all that really.
This is one of the more perfect examples of the kind of technological trap
that we set for ourselves, the lift, the elevator.
I mean, what is it?
It's a steel box, there's some buttons in it, and maybe a trap door for emergencies,
but whoever looks that close.
Except when this happens, where is it?
And even in this situation, closed in with an escape route that we can't handle.
We behave like many of those New Yorkers did.
We strike a light, and we look around to see how badly things are.
And if we find, in this case, an emergency button, absolutely great.
We sit back and we wait for help to come.
We wait for technology to come back and save our lives,
because it's inconceivable that it won't, isn't it?
I mean, if you admit that, you've got to admit that every single day of your life,
in some form or other, you unconsciously walk yourself into a technology trap,
because that's the only way to live in the modern world.
So you don't admit it.
You say, oh, well, in this situation, we'll cope.
But what happens when the effects become widespread, irreversible, devastating?
What happens when, what little resources you have to help you cope?
Give up. Then what?
Well, in all the disaster scenarios you read, what happens is that without power,
technologically-based civilization cracks up rapidly.
Without enough auxiliary power, and most major cities don't have it,
organization is impossible. It's every man for himself, looting and arson followed.
And in a city not prepared to be a fortress, supplies run out fast.
And however frightening the thought of leaving your technological womb
sooner or later, there is nowhere to go but out, away from the danger.
The minute you decide to move, you're on your own, in a way that no modern 20th-century city-dweller
has ever been in his life.
And then the traps begin to close. To start with, do you even know where to go in order to survive?
Did you manage to get a map before you left?
And if you did, how do you get out? Walk?
Drive until you run out of fuel?
Are you ahead of the millions of other people pouring down these roads trying to do?
Just what you're trying to do?
And if they catch up with you, have you got something they need?
And if you have, can you protect yourself?
Did you bring enough food and drink to last as long as necessary?
And if you didn't, where will you get it?
Steel?
How far out will you have to push on until you're far enough out to be safe?
And can you be sure that's far enough?
And even if by some miracle, you finally make it.
Do you know enough to recognise a place to stop when you see it?
I mean, what does survival without technology look like?
The Beto signs up.
So, let's say that finally, somewhere far out into the country, you come across a place that looks right.
And let's say that you've had the good sense and the good luck to look for a farm.
Because that's where food comes from, doesn't it?
OK, so it's a farm, so you decide to stop.
Has anybody got there first?
Or are the owners still here?
Because they're going to need shelter, and people don't give their homes away.
They barricade themselves in.
So, sooner or later, exhausted and desperate,
you may have to make the decision to give up and die.
Or to make somebody else give up and die, because they won't accept you in their home voluntarily.
And what in your comfortable, urban life has ever prepared you for that decision?
OK, let's say by some miracle the place is empty and it's all yours.
Is there enough food in the house? How long will it last?
How will you cook it? Woodfires?
Are you fit enough to chop all the wood you need before winter comes?
If you're lucky, you've got livestock on the farm. Great. Meat.
But can you slaughter and bleed and put your own animal?
OK, supposing you manage that, you've got enough meat to eat until you've eaten all the cows.
But at least you can start running your farm.
But it's a modern farm, remember? It's mechanized.
There's a gasoline pump, but it's empty.
So you can't use the tractor.
What you need is a horse and cart.
But when did you last see a horse and cart on a modern farm?
And everything else here, the saw, the power drills, the light, the sterilizer, the water supply, the sewage system, the hoist, the milking parlor, the pumps, and everything on this controlled panel demands the one thing you don't have.
Electric power.
Everything on this farm that you've found doesn't work. The place is a trap.
But there's nowhere else to go.
The only way you're going to survive is if you find the one thing you need to keep on providing the food you've got to have, and you don't need the mechanized version of that thing.
You need the kind people haven't used in a hundred years.
Ah, you need that kind of plow. You're saved.
Or are you? Because what it comes down to at this point is this. Can you use a plow?
It's taken a series of miracles just to get you this far, and here you are with the biggest miracle of all, a plow and animals to pull it.
So maybe after a few days of fumbling around with the harnesses and the bits and pieces, you manage to yoke up the oxen and plow the land.
And then and only then can you say that you have successfully escaped the wreckage of technological civilization and lived off the land and survived.
If you know how to use the furrow, you plow.
I mean, can you tell the difference between an ear of corn and a geranium seed?
Do you know when to sow whatever it is you think it is?
Do you know what a harvest it and eat the bit that you think isn't poisonous?
I mean, it's no accident that the chain of events triggered off by that relay and the power station back there in Niagara Falls ends here with the plow.
The relay itself doesn't matter.
I mean, any one of a million things could fail and cause our complex civilization to collapse for an hour, for a day, however long, because that's when you find out the extent to which you have to be able to.
The extent to which you are reliant on technology and don't even know it.
That's when you see that it's so interdependent you take one thing away and the whole thing falls down and leaves you with nothing unless you can plow and survive and start the whole process off again from scratch.
And it's no accident that to do that you have to have a plow.
Because it was the plow that triggered everything off, a long way back in the past, after a different set of people also found out that their comfortable life was falling apart.
In a world where events came to a point where a fundamentally new way of life had to be found.
That's exactly what happened about 12,000 years ago. It may be four places on the earth.
Northern India, Syria, Egypt, Central America.
It stopped raining and got very hot.
The result of that change in the weather was to lead to an invention that would trigger the development of a civilization that ends with up in the modern world.
Let me explain that. You see the high grasslands started to dry out, became like this place, and the plants and the animals that had sustained the wandering tribes started to disappear.
People began to die. There was only one thing the survivors could do, head for water.
And so down they came into the great river valleys.
Here in Egypt, that river was the Nile.
And the Nile was an extraordinary river. It rose in two places, for one it brought rotting vegetation and from the other potash.
And any garden will tell you what that means.
When it flooded every year, it dumped compost and fertilizer onto the land.
And the land blew too well.
With easy food, the population grew to where not even the Nile could support it without help.
Faced with starvation, the river dwellers tried planting grain by hand. Not enough.
What solved their problem was an invention that triggered off a series of events which ends with us in our modern technology trap.
Because that invention was to trigger the beginnings of civilization.
Sometimes
This is the first great man-made trigger of change, the plow.
Because with it you know how much harvest you're going to get next year.
And because of that you know you're going to be here next year.
And because of that you can plan for the future.
And after a while when you can produce surplus food,
then that's when things really start to move in the tiny settlements.
With regular food supplies the population explodes.
The village expands.
There are more buildings and they're bigger for bigger families and they're more permanent.
You domesticate animals for their milk and their meat and their skin because they're not there to hunt anymore.
And basket weaving and the twisting of grass to do it teaches you how to spin flax.
And that makes linen.
But it's the grain that causes the fundamental change.
Because with it you bake the bread that is the staple diet on which everybody lives.
And you learn about ovens and about the effect of heat on mud and brick.
But above all you have to have somewhere to store the grain surplus in pots.
But there's so much surplus by now you need the pots to be made faster and you need them to last longer.
So the pot has wheel happens.
Then comes a problem of who does it belong to.
And the only answer to that is this.
Writing.
And the very first writing takes that form.
A name and a symbol for what's inside this pot or a lot of pots or an entire village granary.
And so the little villages grew with their huts and their granaries.
And then almost out of nowhere it seems.
That happened.
The oldest stone building in the world.
The steppe pyramid of King Zozur at Sakara near Cairo.
Built around 2700 BC.
Instanced sophisticated architecture from mud huts in one jump.
How do they do it?
Because of what they'd had to do to feed themselves.
Elegant.
Because the river flooded every year and destroyed landmarks and then retreated leaving the soil to dry out.
They had to do two things.
Find a way of measuring the land so the farmer got his own fields back.
And a way of channeling the water away for use after the flood had gone.
The kind of measurement you need to do those things involves geometry and the type of mathematics a civil engineer uses.
And building canals teaches you to work stone.
If you know stone work and geometry and mathematics you can build pyramids.
Especially for strong central government that was developed to run irrigation schemes in the first place tells you to.
If the pharaoh said he wanted a pointed stone monument that's what he got.
Funny thing is the same drought that drove everybody down to the Nile also preserved the things they built like their tombs for thousands of years.
The stuff on the walls in this tomb for example is 4,500 years old.
A kind of cartoon view of the civilization the plow created.
I mean look here's irrigation.
There are these people carrying water pots.
You see them?
And they carry them across and they pour the water into a garden that has a wall around it.
And then over here look there's a fellow doing a bit of weeding.
There's the plow.
They domesticated oxen.
They tried to domesticate any animal that they could get their hands on.
I mean take a look at this.
Animal flatten its back.
Tights back legs.
Hang onto its front legs.
Stuff food down its throat and hope it'll land to love you.
You didn't get too far with that one.
It was a hyena.
Well you've got a growing community and plenty of spare food and you'll need to protect yourself.
So making weapons becomes very important.
And here on this wall there's a whole thing about handling metals.
Look here are the weights and measures people checking on how much metals going to be used.
Next to them the furnace men.
You see the way they're raising the temperature they're blowing on these tubes to create a draft in the furnace to get the temperature high.
Next to them here's the molten metal being poured into a mold.
And here the fella's beating it flat.
Okay you get yourself a kingdom.
You get what you deserve.
You get bureaucrats.
Here they are.
The scribes.
Writing everything down.
See the pens behind there is?
In this case they're noting taxes.
Here are the people coming in to pay their taxes.
Lead persuasively by the local police.
Here's a policeman with a rod of office.
More policeman.
Here's an Egyptian scruff of the neck. He obviously doesn't want to pay.
If you end up not paying they get out their whips and they tie you to a pole.
And that's what you get for not coming up with the money.
So you have a busy sophisticated society.
You have to have people at the top in charge.
This is the tomb of one of them.
He was a kind of Egyptian choncival responsible directly to the king.
There he is.
His name was Mariruka.
By sometime around 3,200 BC the entire 700 mile length of the Nile from the Mediterranean to Aswan was united and administered by officials like Mariruka.
Each one running what was called a water province.
A section of the irrigation network and of the river under his command.
What held it all together was the king's magic ability as a god to come up year after year with an inundation of the Nile.
And to know exactly how high the waters would go.
Of course it wasn't magic it was his astronomers.
They observed that one particular star, Sirius, rises just before dawn on one particular day the 17th of July every year.
And that day is one day before the flood begins.
They also saw that on average the flood itself came once every 365 days.
Now you put those two facts together.
The star before dawn and the flood.
And you've got yourself a calendar.
And with a calendar you can organize people.
You can give them a date to do something on.
And as for the king's ability to predict how high the water would go well you record the level of the flood every year with a scratch on the wall.
And after a while your experience will tell you early on how high the water is going to be later.
Now in Egypt where water is life.
That kind of knowledge and ability to control gives you the power to build empires.
The ancient temples of Karnak
On the edge of the Nile about 450 miles south of Cairo.
They were the center of Egyptian religion built in the imperial city of Thebes when the Egyptian empire was at its height.
when the Egyptian Empire was at its height,
the greatest power in the world.
This was the New York of the time.
The temples were built over a period of about 2,000 years,
each pharaoh adding his bit,
leaving his name in stone to last forever.
Inside the temple domain, there were 65 towns,
433 gardens and orchards,
400,000 animals,
and it took 80,000 people just to run the place.
Small wonder that centuries afterwards,
the Greeks and the Romans came here
and gored like peasants at a civilization
that made their efforts look like well-dressed mud huts.
It still has that effect today.
Here you come here from the great modern cities,
full of the immense power of modern technology.
At your fingertips, press a button, turn a switch,
and this place stops you dead.
And then, just when you think you've got the measure of Karnak,
you come here at dawn to the hall of columns,
one of the most massive structures ever built.
And anything I was going to say isn't enough.
Look at it.
The Egyptians built an empire and ran it with a handful of technology.
The wheel, the irrigation canals, the loom, a calendar, pen and ink,
some cutting tools, simple metallurgy, and the plow,
the invention that triggered it all off.
And yet look how complex and sophisticated their civilization was
and how soon it happened after that first man-made harvest.
The Egyptian plow and those of the few other civilizations
that sprang up around the world at the same time
gave us control over nature,
and at the same time tied us for good
to the things that we invent so that tomorrow will be better than today.
The Egyptians knew that.
That's why they had gods, to make sure their systems didn't fail.
Karnak was the first great statement of what technology could do
with unlimited manpower and the approval of the gods.
CHEERING
Ironically, the modern equivalent lies again in the desert.
This time, the nomads also settled by a river, a river of oil.
But what it took the pharaohs four thousand years to build
took the Kuwaitis four thousand days.
What's happened in Kuwait, the change from a nomadic existence
to being able to buy and use everything modern technology has to offer,
has come in much less than one generation.
CHEERING
Kuwait represents the immense power of technology
using the way most of us have never experienced,
because we've lived with a kind of change it can bring for more than 100 years.
Here, it's been focused.
Change has been instant and total.
Hello, Nain.
Hello.
I'm from the country.
You're here.
Kuwait has suddenly become like New York,
or any other of the great urban islands of technology,
totally dependent on that technology.
Like them, without it, Kuwait would return to the desert.
Hello, Sharon?
Hi, how are you?
Hey, listen.
I'm coming to spend my Christmas in New York, OK?
You see how increasingly the only way we
and the advanced industrial nations with our bewildering technology network
can survive is by selling bewilderment and dependence on technology
to the rest of the world.
Or is it not bewilderment and dependence,
but a healthier, wealthier, better way of living than the old way?
And yet, whether or not you dress up technology to look local,
the technology network is the same.
And as it spreads, will it spread the ability to use machines
as we do without understanding them?
Somebody said a few years ago about the way our modern world affects us all,
if you understand something today,
that means it must already be obsolete.
Or to put it another way,
never have so many people understood so little about so much.
So why are we in this position?
Why is our modern industrialized world the way it is?
And not some different way, with different technology,
doing different things to us.
Well, that's what the rest of this series is going to look at.
You saw just now that the plow and irrigation kicked us all off,
and that an invention acts rather like a trigger,
because once it's there, it changes the way things are,
and that change stimulates the production of another invention,
which in turn causes change, and so on.
Why those inventions happened between 6,000 years ago and now,
where they happened and when they happened,
is a fascinating blend of accident, genius craftsmanship,
geography, religion, war, money, ambition.
Above all, at some point,
everybody is involved in the business of change,
not just the so-called great men.
Given what they knew at the time,
and a moderate amount of what's up here,
I hope to show you that you or I could have done just what they did,
or come close to it,
because at no time did an invention come out of thin air
into somebody's head like that.
You just had to put a number of bits and pieces
that were already there together in the right way.
Following the trail of events from some point in the past,
to a piece of modern technology,
is rather like a detective story with you as the detective,
knowing only as much as the people in the past knew,
and like them having to guess at what was likely to happen next.
So, the trigger that sets off the first of those detective stories
is to be a very good story.
is that.
And I'd like to leave you with one question before next time.
Why does a modern invention that fundamentally affects the lives
of every single human being on this planet
begin 2,600 years ago with somebody doing this?
MUSIC